如果你拿起任何有关机器人技术的标准教科书，你会发现参考
If you pick up any of the standard textbooks about robotics, you will find reference to
Denavit和Hartenberg表示法。这是以JacquesDenavit和RichardHartenberg的名字命名的
Denavit and Hartenberg notation. This is named after Jacques Denavit and Richard Hartenberg
他在1955年写了一篇文章，后来写了一本非常非常一般的书
who in 1955 wrote an article and later, a book which proposed a very, very general way
描述串行链接机制，我们看过的大多数机器人都是串行的
of describing serial link mechanisms and most of the robots that we've looked at are serial
链接操纵器。因此，Denavit和Hartenberg符号特别适用于此
link manipulators. So, the Denavit and Hartenberg notation is particularly applicable for this
机制类。
class of mechanism.
现在在大多数标准教科书中。人们开始介绍这一点
Now in most of the standard textbooks. People start off with introducing this particular
符号。就个人而言，我发现这种符号有点复杂而且不是特别直观。
notation. Personally, I find the notation somewhat complex and not particularly intuitive.
所以，我在这个特定的讲座中所做的就是把它留到最后。一个关键方面
So, what I've done in this particular lecture is left it until the end. A key aspect of
Denavit-Hartenberg表示机器人中的每个关节仅由4个参数描述。
Denavit-Hartenberg notation is that each joint in the robot is described simply by 4 parameters.
所以，让我们从一个非常简单的串行链接操作开始，即2个联合机器人
So, let's start off with a very simple serial link manipulative that 2 joint robot that
我们以前见过很多次。每个关节通过前一个链接连接
we've seen a number of times before. Each joint is attached via a link to the previous
联合。所以在这里，我们可以看到连接到连接的链路1的连接1
joint. So here, we can see joint 1 which is connected to link 1 which is connected to
连杆2连接到连杆2.它们的连杆是刚性的，但关节可以移动。他们
joint 2 which is connected to link 2. Their links are rigid but the joints can move. They
这里可以是旋转的例子，也可以是棱柱形或滑动接头
can be either rotational as an example shown here or they can be prismatic or sliding joints
我们以前谈过的。
that we've talked about before.
每个关节连接到链接，每个链接连接到关节，除了第一个和
Every joint connects to links and every link connects to joints except for the first and
最后一个链接第一个链接是不移动的机器人的基础参考那个
last link. The first link is the base of the robot which does not move refer to that as
链接0和最后一个链接是in-defector或附加到机器人的in-defector。
link 0 and the last link is the in-defector or is attached to the in-defector of the robot.
如果一个机器人有n关节，那么它必须有n加1个链接，包括
If a robot has got n-joints then, it must have n plus 1 links, that's including the
第0个链接或基数。Denavit-Hartenberg表示法的基础是我们附加一个坐标框架
0th link or the base. Fundamental to the Denavit-Hartenberg notation is we attach a coordinate frame to
机器人每个环节的远端。所以在这里，我们可以看到链接J显示为蓝色和
the far end of every link of the robot. So here, we can see link J shown in blue and
我们将坐标框架J附加到链接J的远端，即链接的末尾
we attach the coordinate frame J to the far end of link J that is the end of the link
这是最接近机器人工具的。然后，我们描述该链接框架的姿势
that's closest to the robots tool. Then, we describe the pose of that link frame with
尊重前一个关节的链接框架。所以，这是一个相对的姿势和这个
respect to the link frame of the previous joint. So, this is a relative pose and this
是我们现在应该熟悉的概念。这是坐标系的相对姿势
is a concept we should be familiar with now. This is a relative pose from coordinate frame
J-1协调框架J.
J-1 to coordinate frame J.
在Denavit-Hartenberg表示法中，链接变换由齐次表示
In the Denavit-Hartenberg notation, the link transform is represented by a homogeneous
变换矩阵，通常由字母A表示，并且包括数字
transformation matrix which is typically denoted by the letter A and it comprises a number
基本变换它包括围绕Z轴的旋转。翻译
of elementary transformations. It comprises a rotation around the Z axis. A translation
沿Z轴。沿X轴的平移和围绕X轴的旋转。它的
along the Z axis. A translation along the X axis and a rotation around the X axis. It's
非常简洁。它允许我们描述2链接坐标之间的关系
very concise. It allows us to describe the relationship between the 2 link coordinate
只需4个参数，即θ，D，A和alpha。让我们看看它在实践中是如何运作的。
frames by simply 4 parameters, theta, D, A and alpha. Let's see how that works in practice.
所以在这里，我们有红色链接J-1和连接到链接J-1的坐标系。第一件事
So here, we have in red link J-1 and the coordinate frame attached to link J-1. First thing that
我们要做的是围绕Z轴旋转该坐标系的量为theta
we're going to do is to rotate that coordinate frame around its Z axis by an amount theta
J，我们旋转轴。接下来我们要做的就是翻译那个坐标
J and we rotate the axis. The next thing we're going to do is to translate that coordinate
沿Z轴框架的数量为D，然后，我们将沿着它转换它
frame along the Z axis by an amount D and then, we're going to translate it along the
X轴为J，最后，我们将围绕X轴旋转一个角度
X axis by an amount J and finally, we're going to rotate it around the X axis by an angle
alpha和现在，它看起来像这样。
alpha and now, it looks like this.
所以，我们通过应用4个基本变换从框架J-1移动到框架J，
So, we have moved from the frame J-1 to the frame J by applying 4 elementary transformations,
2个翻译和2个轮换。您可能会问我们如何才能使用4来完成此操作
2 translations and 2 rotations. You're probably asking is how can we do this using only 4
参数，因为一个姿势有2个组件。它有一个我们的翻译组件
parameters because a pose has got 2 components. It's got a translational component which we
由3个数字描述，它有一个我们用3个数字描述的旋转。例如，
described by 3 numbers and it has a rotation which we described by 3 numbers. For example,
滚动，俯仰，偏航角或欧拉角。我们如何只用4个数字呢？好吧，
roll, pitch, yaw angles or Euler angles. How do we do it with just 4 numbers? Well, the
这有效的原因是Denavit-Hartenberg符号需要在哪里限制
reason this works is that the Denavit-Hartenberg notation requires some constraints on where
我们放置坐标框架。第一个约束是框架J的X轴相交
we place the coordinate frames. The first constraint is that the X axis of frame J intersects
框架J-1的Z轴。第二个约束是框架J的X轴是垂直的
the Z axis of frame J-1. The second constraint is that the X axis of frame J is perpendicular
到框架J-1的Z轴。虽然，亲戚中只有6个自由度
to the Z axis of frame J-1. Although, there are only 6 degrees of freedom in a relative
姿势。我们引入了2个约束的事实意味着我们只能使用它来描述它
pose. The fact that we've introduced 2 constraints means that we can describe this using only
4个参数。有一个有趣的，往往令人困惑的结果，这意味着
4 parameters. There's an interesting and often confusing consequence of this and that means
链接帧不一定在链接本身上，这就是它
that the link frames are not necessarily on the link itself and this is something that
当人们开始学习Denavit-Hartenberg时，往往会让人感到困惑
quite often confuses people when they're starting off and learning about Denavit-Hartenberg
符号。
notation.
旋转关节的轴必须与该关节坐标的Z轴对齐
The axis of a rotational joint has to be aligned with the Z axis of that joints coordinate
帧。Denavit-Hartenberg符号要求关节轴J平行于
frame. The Denavit-Hartenberg notation requires that the axis of joint J is parallel to the
坐标系的Z轴，但它不是连接到链接J的坐标系
Z axis of a coordinate frame but it's not the coordinate frame attached to link J. The
关节轴J与前一个坐标系的Z轴对齐，即坐标
axis of joint J is aligned with the Z axis of the previous coordinate frame, that's coordinate
框架J-1再次，这对于开始学习的人来说是一个令人困惑的方面
frame J-1 and again, this is a confusing aspect for people who is starting out learning about
这种表示法。对于棱柱形或滑动关节的情况，运动必须同时进行
this notation. For the case of a prismatic or sliding joint, the motion must be along
Z轴。因此，对于旋转关节，围绕前一帧的Z轴旋转
the Z axis. So, for rotational joint, rotate around the Z axis of the previous frame for
一个棱柱形的关节，我们沿着前一帧的Z轴平移。
a prismatic joint, we translate along the Z axis of the previous frame.
从1个链接到下一个链接的帧的相对姿势由4个基本变换描述。
The relative pose from the frame of 1 link to the next is described by 4 elementary transformations.
对于n-link机器人，我们可以堆叠这些基本变换的组和每个
For an n-link robot, we can stack groups of these elementary transformations and each
group包含4个参数，描述了1个链接帧和1之间的关系
group contains 4 parameters which described the relationship between 1 link frame and
下一个。如果机器人已经获得了所有的旋转关节，则关节角度对应于
the next. If the robot has got all revolute joints then, the joint angles correspond to
这里显示的theta值。所以，这些是联合变量。它们随机器人而变化
the theta values shown here. So, these are the joint variables. They change as the robot
移动。所有其他参数，D'，A和alpha都是常数。
moves. All the other parameters, the D's, the A's and the alpha's are all constant.
它们是特定机器人的机械设计的功能。我们考虑一下
They're a function of the mechanical design of the particular robot. Let's consider a
有棱柱关节的机器人。它的第二个关节是棱柱形的。自从第一次
robot that has got a prismatic joint. Its second joint is prismatic. Since the first
联合是旋转的，我们在这里替换Q1。对于棱柱形的第二个关节，我们
joint is revolute, we substitute Q1 in here. For the second joint which is prismatic, we
在这里替换Q2。对于像这样的关节，theta2是一个常数，就像A2和alpha一样
substitute Q2 in here. For a joint like this, theta 2 is a constant just like A2 and alpha
它们是这种特殊机器人的机械设计的功能。
2. They are the function of the mechanical design of this particular robot.
Denavit-Hartenberg符号的巨大优势在于它使我们能够非常简洁
The great advantage of the Denavit-Hartenberg notation is that it allows us to very concisely
描述一个机器人。因此，对于2链路机器人，可以简单地通过这样的表来描述。
describe a robot. So, for the 2 link robot, it can be described simply by a table like this.
我们每个Denavit-Hartenberg参数都有1列，每个关节有一行
We have 1 column for each of the Denavit-Hartenberg parameters and we have one row for each joint
机器人关节变量Q1和Q2位于θ列中，因为它们是旋转的
of the robot. The joint variables Q1 and Q2 lie in the theta column because they are revolute
关节。D值均为0.沿Z轴没有平移，因为此机器人存在
joints. The D values are all 0. There are no translations along the Z axis because this robot exists
在一个平面中，2个链接长度出现在A列中，并且alpha值都等于0。
in a plane and the 2 link lengths appear in the A column and the alpha values are all equal to 0.
因此，这个非常紧凑的表格完整地描述了我们称之为机器人的运动学。
So, this very compact table completely describes what we call the kinematics of the robot.
机器人工具箱设置得很好，可以处理Denavit-Hartenberg符号。
The robotics toolbox is very well set-up to deal with Denavit-Hartenberg notation.
我将创建一个Denavit-Hartenberg矩阵，该矩阵中的每一行代表一个单独的矩阵
I'm going to create a Denavit-Hartenberg matrix and each row in this matrix represents a single
链接。这就像我们刚才看到的桌子一样。现在，我要进入
link. It's just like the table we looked at a moment ago. Now, I'm going to enter the
与该表的列对应的数字;theta，D，A和alpha为第一个
numbers corresponding to the columns of that table; theta, D, A and alpha for the first
对于第二个关节的联合和theta，D，A和alpha以及完成矩阵偏移，我有
joint and theta, D, A and alpha for the second joint and finish that matrix offset, I have
一个简单的2乘4矩阵，包含一个2关节机器人的Denavit-Hartenberg参数。
a simple 2 by 4 matrix which contains a Denavit-Hartenberg parameters for a 2 joint robot.
虽然我可以创建一个机器人对象，但我会将它放入工作空间变量R和
While I can create a robot object, I'm going to put it into the workspace variable R and
我使用工具箱函数串行链接，并传入Denavit-Hartenberg参数
I use the toolbox function serial link and I pass in the Denavit-Hartenberg parameter
矩阵，结果是在我的工作区和串行链接中创建的串行链接对象
matrix and the result is a serial link object created in my workspace and the serial link
对象代表机器人手臂。我们可以在这里看到它显示了Denavit-Hartenberg
object represents a robot arm. We can see here that it's displayed the Denavit-Hartenberg
表格形式的参数。我们将在底部附近有一些额外的参数
parameters in table form. There are some additional parameters around the bottom which we will
很快介绍。
introduce shortly.
一旦我有了这个对象，我可以在它上面执行一些简单的函数我可以绘制
Once I have this object then, I can perform some simple functions on it I can plot the
具有配置的机器人，其中关节角度可能是0.2辐射度和0.3辐射度
robot with the configuration where the joint angles are perhaps 0.2 radiance and 0.3 radiance
这就是它的样子，我也可以制作一个教学吊坠。
and this is what it looks like and I can also create a teach pendant.
所以，这里是教导，带来我们以前见过的滑块允许我
So, here is the teach pendant, brings up the sliders that we've seen before allows me to
移动这个机器人手臂的关节。
move the joints of this robot arm.
机器人对象还具有正向运动学方法。所以，我可以将它应用于机器人
The robot object also has a forward kinematic method. So, I can apply that to the robot
宾语。这是fkine方法，如果我传入，例如，关节角度0.2和
object. It's the fkine method and if I pass in for instance, the joint angles 0.2 and
0.3，它将为我返回一个均匀的变换，表示该机器人的入侵者的姿势。
0.3, it will return for me a homogeneous transformation representing the pose of the in-defector of that robot.
我们在这里可以看到X坐标和Y坐标，这里的矩阵代表
We can see here the X coordinate and the Y coordinate and this matrix over here represents
这个机器人的入侵者的方向。对于像Puma这样更复杂的机器人
the orientation of the in-defector of this robot. For a more complex robot like the Puma
在图560中，可以用这样的表来描述。再次，该表有4列但是
560, it can be described by a table like this. Once again, the table has got 4 columns but
在这种情况下，它有6行，因为有6个关节，因为这个机器人都是旋转的，
in this case, it's got 6 rows because there are 6 joints, because this robot is all revolute,
我们在theta列中找到所有联合动词。在D列和A列中，
we find all the joint verbals in the theta column. In the D column and the A column,
我们找到了许多与Puma机器人的物理长度相对应的数字。
we find a number of numbers which correspond to physical lengths on the Puma robot.
上臂的长度，下臂的长度，一些水平的偏移和
The length of the upper arm, the length of the lower arm, some horizontal offsets and
所以在alpha列中，我们发现了pi或2为负的旋转次数
so on and the alpha column, we find a number of rotations which either pi on 2 or negative
pion2，他们说了一个关节旋转轴和下一个关节的方向
pi on 2 and they say something about the orientation of 1 joints rotational axis and the next joints
旋转轴。
rotational axis.
在我们处理的时候，MATLAB和机器人工具箱真正发挥作用
Where MATLAB and robotics toolbox really come into their own is when we're dealing with
复杂的机器人，有6个或更多关节的机器人。我可以导入古典彪马的模型
complex robots, those with 6 joints or more. I can import a model of the classical Puma
560机器人，它在工作区中创建了一个名为P560的口头语，我可以看看
560 robot and it's created a verbal in the workspace called P560 and I can have a look
在那里，我们在这里看到一个表格，其中包含描述的Denavit-Hartenberg参数
at that and here, we see a table which contains the Denavit-Hartenberg parameters that described
那特定的机器人。
that particular robot.
现在，我可以将该机器人绘制成特定的关节角度配置。现在，我要走了
Now, I can plot that robot for a particular joint angle configuration. Now, I'm going
使用由Puma560中的函数定义的变量QZ。我们可以看到
to use the variable QZ which was defined by the function in the Puma 560. We can see that
在这里工作区。它是一个有6个元素的向量，都等于0，在这里，我们
over here in the workspace. It's a vector with 6 elements all equal to 0 and here, we
在配置中看到机器人，其所有关节角度都等于0.另一种配置
see the robot in the configuration where all its joint angles are equal to 0. Another configuration
定义的是这一个QR，它被称为机器人的准备姿势和这个
that was defined is this one QR which was referred to the robot's ready pose and this
是指手臂指向空中。
is with the arm pointing straight up into the air.
我也可以在这个特殊的机器人上设置一个示教器。在这里，我们看到了它。现在我
I can also bring up a teach pendant on this particular robot. Here, we see it. Now, I
有6个滑块，每个滑块各1个。我可以将它旋转到腰部以上。我可以动了
have got 6 sliders, 1 for each of its joints. I can rotate it above the waist. I can move
肩膀向下。我可以举起肘部。我会向下移动肘部，向下移动一下
the shoulder down. I can lift the elbow up. I'll move the elbow down, move it down a bit
更多，我可以围绕腰部旋转它，所以我们可以看到发生了什么。
more and I can rotate it around the waist so we can see what's going on.
我们可以在那里看到in-defector坐标系，如果我调整了腕关节角度，
We can see the in-defector coordinate frame there and if I adjust the wrist joint angles,
我们可以看到入侵者的方向在变化。该物体具有前向运动学特性
we can see the orientation of the in-defector changing. The object has got a forward kinematic
方法。所以，如果我要求一组关节角度的正向运动学，也许是关节
method. So, if I asked for the forward kinematics for a set of joint angles, perhaps the joint
角度等于0.1,0.2,0.3。我只是在这里编造一些数字。这是同质的
angles equal 0.1, 0.2, 0.3. I'm just making up some numbers here. This is the homogeneous
转换代表这个6轴Puma560机器人的入侵者的姿势。
transformation which represents the pose of the in-defector of this 6 axis Puma 560 robot.
因此，使用非常通用的数学符号，我们可以说是n关节机器人的姿势
So, to use a very general mathematical notation, we can say that the pose of an n-joint robot
我将写作PSIN是一个函数，函数是K，K代表运动学，
which I'm going to write as PSI N is a function and the function is K and K stands for kinematics,
我们将很快简洁地定义一个术语，它是联合配置的一个功能，
a term that we will define concisely shortly and it's a function of the joint configuration,
这是N个联合变量的向量。
that's the vector of the N joint variables.
它们可能是角度，或者在滑动关节的情况下它们可能是链接。矢量
They might be angles or they might be links in the case of a sliding joint. A vector of
关节角度，链接偏移的矢量，链接长度的矢量和什么的矢量
joint angles, a vector of link offsets, a vector of link lengths and a vector of what
被称为链接扭曲和关节类型的向量。
are called link twists and a vector of joint types.
Sigma是一个包含R或P元素的向量，它们表示是否
Sigma is a vector that contains elements which are either R or P and they indicate whether
关节是旋转的或棱柱形的。在旋转关节的情况下，我们替换
the joint is revolute or prismatic. In the case of a revolute joint, we substitute the
从Q的相应元素和棱柱接头的θ的相应元素，我们替代
corresponding element of theta from the corresponding element of Q and for prismatic joint, we substitute
D的相应元素来自Q的相应元素.D的所有其他元素，
the corresponding element of D from the corresponding element of Q. All the other elements of D,
theta，A和alpha是不变的。
theta, A and alpha are constant.